I want to talk today
about efficient markets, which is a
theory that is a half-truth, I will say.
Before I start, I wanted to
just give a few thoughts about
David Swenson's lecture last period.
Let me say, first of
all, the efficient markets is a
hypothesis, or the efficient markets theory is a theory that
markets efficiently incorporate all public
information.
And that therefore, you cannot beat the market, because the
market has all the information in it.
You think you're smarter than the market, that you know
something?
No, the market knows more than you do.
And you'll find out that the market wins every time.
That's the efficient markets hypothesis.
So, it's a very far-reaching hypothesis.
It means that
you can't
beat the market.
You can't beat the market.
So, that was a very rudimentary introduction to
today's lecture.
But here I brought in
David Swenson, who is claimed to
have beaten the market consistently since 1985, and
dramatically.
And so, what do we make of that?
That's the subject of today's lecture.
By the way, after Class
1 of you came up, thank you.
It was nice.
I don't know where you are.
One of you came up and
thanked Swenson for his scholarship at
Yale.
Yale now has need-blind admissions for the world.
And so, people, not just
from the United States, people are
helped out, so that people
who manage to meet the high
admissions standards here make it possible to actually come
here.
And that's partly, that's substantially David Swenson who
did that.
Because it's not just the generosity of the university.
They have to have the money to do it.
And so, somehow he seems to have made it.
Now, I know that there are still many cynics.
The efficient markets hypothesis remains, it has a lot
of adherence still.
And as I say, it's a half-truth.
So, some people will say, Swenson was just lucky.
And I say, well, how can you say that?
Well, how could he have been
lucky for 25 years in a row?
Well, not every single year, but pretty much.
And they'd say, well, but
you're picking the one guy out
of millions who was just the luckiest.
So, those arguments are made.
So, anyway, one of you asked
a question, which I thought was
very good at the end.
And that is, what is the
best way to get a job?
And that's why in all
of my discussion about Swenson and
all of his talk, he never mentioned the Sharpe ratio.
Because as we said, the
Sharpe ratio corrects for risk-taking.
It's easy to get, that
was one of our fundamental lessons
when we showed you the efficient portfolio frontier
and the tangency line.
You can get any expected
return you want at the expense
of higher uncertainty.
You do a very risky
portfolio, and you have high expected
returns because of the risk,
if the risk is measured right.
And so, but I think that's
a very good question, because I
caught myself not correcting for it.
I just said, Yale's portfolio
had a high return, and I
didn't correct for standard deviation of return.
So, David Swenson.
And his answer, as you'll recall, essentially said, he
doesn't believe in Sharpe ratios, because we can't
measure the standard deviation.
So, the Sharpe ratio is
the excess return of a portfolio
over the market, divided by the standard deviation of the
return.
Okay?
And that scales it down.
So, if the excess return is
very high, but it also has a
very high standard deviation, that shows they were just
taking risks.
And so, the Sharpe ratio would reveal that.
But Swenson said, I don't
think that you can measure the
standard deviation of returns.
Isn't that what his answer was?
You were here.
I may not be quoting him exactly right.
So, why wouldn't you be
able to measure the standard deviation
of returns?
And I think there's, he gave
a reason, which was that, well,
when you're looking at a broad
portfolio like Yale's, a lot of
the things in there are private assets.
So, you can't just say,
well, it's equity, or that means
privately held, so it's not traded on stock exchanges.
Or it's real estate.
Real estate is only traded
every 10 years or 20 years.
And so, who knows what it's worth?
All you have is an appraisal.
But that's just some appraiser's estimate.
So, it's not, the standard deviation would be artificially
low.
So, he's right about that.
But I think there's even more to that.
More to the.
I know there's more to this.
But I think there's more to this.
And the point that I wanted to
make is that you can do a,
suppose you're managing money, OK?
And suppose the world out there
is evaluating you by your Sharpe
ratio, OK?
And suppose you have no ethics, OK?
Well, you just want money.
This isn't so obviously criminal.
I suppose.
But so, you say, I just want
to have the best Sharpe ratio for
a number of years running, OK?
And I'll get more and more
people that will put money in
my investment fund.
And eventually, I don't care what happens, I'll move to
Brazil or something.
Or some foreign.
I mean, to pick out one.
I want to get out
of here with the money, OK?
So, all I have to do is
fool people into thinking I have a
high Sharpe ratio for a while.
So, what do I do?
Well, there's an interesting, you know, there's a lot of
papers on this, but I'm going
to cite one by Professor Getzman
and co-authors here at Yale.
It's actually Getzman, Ibbotson, Spiegel and Welch.
Well, maybe I'll put all their names.
But it's interesting.
There's an interesting paper on this
by, well, there's a lot of
papers on this, but I'm going
to cite one by Professor Getzman.
So, Roger Ibbotson, his professor here, Matt Spiegel and
Ivo Welch.
What they did is, they calculated the optimal strategy
for someone who wants to
play games with the Sharpe ratio,
all right?
So, you want to fool investors
and get a spuriously high Sharpe
ratio.
And they found out what
the optimal strategy is, and that
is to get rid of
the, to sell off the tail.
And that's the way you get
rid of the tails of your
distribution of returns.
So, if your return distribution
looks like this, this is return,
okay, and you have a probability distribution, say,
a bell-shaped curve, okay, and so, the mean and standard
deviation of this would be
the inputs to the Sharpe ratio.
But if you're a cynical and
you want to play tricks, what you
can do is sell the upper tail.
So, which is very, these are very unlikely good events.
Sell them and get money now.
And then double up on the lower tail.
So, you push the lower tail
to something like that, and you
wipe out the upper tail, so
it goes like that, all right?
So, that means you will
get money, because you've sold the
upper tail.
You would do that by selling call.
We haven't talked about options yet,
but you could do it by
selling calls on the upper tail.
So, that's the way you do it.
All right.
So, you would do this by writing out-of-the-money calls.
And you would do this by writing out-of-the-money puts.
Okay, but what you do is, you
kill the, you make it so that
there's really a bad year.
It's going to be a
doozer bad year for your investors.
And if there's ever a good
year, then, hey, you won't get
it, all right?
Well, these good or bad years occur only infrequently.
So, in the meantime, you're making profits from these sales
and you have a high Sharpe ratio.
But little do they know
that nothing, you know, you're not
going to get a good year.
You see, nothing, you've sold off the tails.
And so, nothing happens for
many years, and you just look
like the best guy there.
So, that's an example.
Now, it turns out that this is not just academic.
There was a company called Integral Investment Management
that did something like this strategy.
It was a hedge fund.
And so, it was Integral Investment Management.
It did something like this by trading in options.
And it got lots of investors, put millions in them.
Notably, the Art Institute of Chicago put $43 million into
this fund and its associated funds.
And then, in 2001, when
the market dropped a lot, Art
Institute of Chicago was wiped out.
They lost almost all of their $43 million.
And so, they got really
angry and they sued this company
because they said, you didn't tell us.
What have you been doing?
And then, well, the company
pointed out in its defense that
it actually said somewhere in
the fine print that if you're
going to sell something, you
have to have a good deal.
And if markets go down more
than 30%, there would be a
problem.
And somehow, nobody at the
Art Institute, nobody read that or
figured it out.
They thought the guy was a genius, because this company
had the highest Sharpe ratio in the industry.
All right?
You see what they're doing?
They're playing tricks.
They're making it look like there's less risk than there
really is.
And there's a strategy to do that.
But it didn't end well for Integral Investment Management,
because.
The Art Institute of Chicago
managed to stick them on other
things.
They disclosed this.
They told people that they were doing this strategy.
The artists didn't figure it out.
But there were other dishonesties that they got.
They nailed these guys on.
So, this comes back.
Let me say, what Goetzmann
and his co-authors did is, they
showed that you can play tricks
with the – you can play
a lot of tricks in finance.
But one of them is play
a trick with the Sharpe ratio.
But their trick was very explicit.
It involved particular portfolio composition,
involving options.
And any professional would immediately know that that's a
trick.
And it didn't work for these guys.
They were too aggressive in their manipulation.
But you can do subtler things
as a portfolio manager to get
your Sharpe ratio up.
And you can do that.
Instead of manipulating with special derivatives positions,
you could just buy companies that have large left tails.
They have a small probability of massive losses.
Right?
And you haven't done anything except pick a stock.
And nobody knows whether it really has a small probability
of massive losses.
Right?
And you could systematically invest in that.
And then you'd have a
high Sharpe ratio for a while.
And then you'd just blow up and lose everything eventually.
I was thinking of an example from recent news.
What about the strategy of investing in Egyptian companies
that are tied to Mubarak?
Okay.
It might have looked very
good for a long time, right?
But the companies might have been underpriced, because
they're not going to be able to do that.
Right?
What were they doing?
But they aren't really getting into it.
Right?
That's a bigometris Karol.
That was powerful.
Thanks for the presentation.
Thank you so much.
Thanks.
So, what I'm getting at is
really, what is the essence of
Swenson's skill or contribution?
It's not his ability to manipulate Sharpe ratios or
numbers like that.
I think what it has to me,
in my mind, is something to do
with character and his real self and his real objective.
And this gets at what
people in finance are really doing.
I think that when you
take a finance course in a
university, you may not get
a proper appreciation of how one
in a career in finance develops a reputation for
integrity.
Nobody can really judge what you're doing as an investor,
because they can't judge it from the statistics.
Even though we've developed this knowledge, we can't
judge it from the statistics.
And so, you end up
with this nice theory about Sharpe
ratios and the like.
You end up judging the
person and what the person's real
objectives are.
So, I'll probably come back to that theme again.
Let me also say this about doing the Getzman.
Do you understand this strategy?
It's a matter of, it's like selling, investing in
securities with time bombs in them,
that are going to go off
eventually.
And they look good for
a while, but they'll blow up.
What does the law say about this?
Well, the law in the United States and other countries
emphasizes that an investment manager must not fail to
disclose relevant information about a security.
And it has to be more than boilerplate disclosure.
You could write a prospectus,
and you could say, for say,
integral investment management, you could write up a
prospectus.
And then say, but of course,
past returns are not a guide
to the future, and something could go wrong.
That's a boilerplate disclosure.
Because people think, well, that's what everybody says.
The law says that you have to actually actively disclose.
If there's something that's relevant that would make your
statistics misleading, you have to get their attention
and explain it to them.
That's the law.
So, I think it's laws
like that, and it's the development
of character.
So, it's not something that we specialize in academia.
Well, we are.
We're trying to develop character, I suppose.
But it's not just sharp ratios.
And I think that tendencies to
rely on numbers like this has
led to errors in the past.
So, let me go more directly into today's lecture.
And it's about the efficient markets hypothesis, which is,
in the United States, the most common hypothesis.
And it's not just sharp ratios.
It is, to me, a fascinating theory, which is not
completely true, which makes it all the more interesting.
The first statement that I could find, I'm interested in
the history of thought.
So, the first statement of the efficient markets hypothesis
that I could find was
in a book by George Gibson.
I'm not good at chalk.
It breaks on me.
I'm too aggressive with chalk.
I'll try to be more gentle.
George Gibson, who wrote a book in 1889,
called The History of Thought.
It's called The Stock Exchanges of London, Paris,
and New York.
And he wrote, I'm quoting George Gibson, 1889, when
shares become publicly known in an open market, the value
which they acquire there may
be regarded as the judgment of
the best intelligence concerning them.
He described the stock market
as a kind of voting machine,
where people vote.
If you think a share is
worth more, you're going to have to
vote by buying it.
If you think it's worth less
than it's in the market, you
sell it.
And everybody in the world can do that.
It's open to the public.
So, the smartest people get into it.
And they soon make a lot of
money doing it, so they have a
lot of votes.
So, the smarter people have more votes.
And you've got everyone there.
If anyone has a special clue,
they go right in and they buy,
if it's positive, or they sell if it's negative.
So, the smartest people, they're going to have to buy.
And the better people go right in there and aggressively
affect the value, until it's right.
And then there's no incentive to buy or sell.
The other thing about Gibson,
I should have copied the quote,
but as I remember from
the book, he says something, in
our modern electric age, information flows with the
speed of light.
And I was thinking, what
is he talking about in 1889?
Well, you know what he's talking about, the telegraph.
And in fact, they had a telegraph.
They had ticker machines.
They were electronic printers that would print out stock
quotes.
So, they were really in the information age by 1889.
So, this is what happened.
Gibson said, you can't beat the market.
It's just smarter, because it's
like Wikipedia is smarter than
any one of us, right?
Because it puts together all
the thinking of all the people.
Well, they had Wikipedia of
a sort, because they had the
price.
They had the price.
So, that is the statement.
He didn't use the word efficient markets.
Actually, I tried to find the origin of efficient markets.
Sometimes in the 19th century, people would say efficient
markets.
But it wasn't a cliché yet.
It wasn't a phrase that would be recognizable.
It would be a chance.
Even in this context, they
didn't use the word efficient markets.
Even in this context, they would use it.
But it was not a name for a theory yet.
The next efficient markets theorist
I had, and I put this
on your reading list, Charles
Conant, who wrote a 1904 book
called Wall Street and the Country.
Wall Street and the Country.
I put one chapter on that on
the reading list, because it was a
statement of the efficient markets hypothesis.
Which was remarkably well written, I thought.
He starts out the chapter by pointing
out that a lot of people think
speculation is a kind of
gambling or a kind of evil.
Speculating on the stock market,
that sounds like some wild activity
that ought to be ruled out.
Then he said, you know,
how can that possibly be true?
The stock market is a central
instance of the efficient markets hypothesis.
It is a central institution of all modern economies.
To think that it's just
gambling, it just defies common sense.
But then he goes on and
describes what it is that it does.
And there's some really nice passages in Conant's book.
In one passage he says, suppose for
a moment that stock markets of the world
were closed, what would happen?
And he said, no one
would know what anything is worth.
No one could make any calculations.
No one could make any calculated decisions.
He said that, in fact, capital
moves around from one industry to another
in respect of the prices
that are quoted in these markets.
And if you didn't see
the prices, you would be blind.
It's often said about the Soviet
economy, which did not have stock markets
or financial markets, that they relied on
prices in the rest of the world.
And they didn't plan very well, because
they didn't know what anything was worth.
But at least they had the rest of the world.
And they thought, well, that's an approximation to
what prices ought to be in the Soviet Union.
So, they were really relying on these.
So, then I just wanted to just reiterate
a little bit about the intuition of efficient markets.
The idea is that if you trade securities,
the advantage to being there a little
bit ahead of anyone else is enormous, right?
If you know five minutes before the other
investors about some good news or bad news,
either way, it doesn't matter,
you know it five minutes earlier,
you jump right in and trade.
You trade ahead of them, and prices haven't changed yet.
You make money.
So, that has created an industry that speeds information.
The first such industry that
I would like to talk about,
the first such industry that I
would tell you about is Reuters.
Mr. Reuters, I think in the 1840s, before the telegraph,
created a financial information
service using carrier pigeons.
You know, these are birds.
And so, when he was in London with some information,
they had carrier pigeons that were brought from Paris.
And as soon as new information came out,
they would take the foot of
the little bird and let it go,
and it would fly to Paris.
It would go to its roosting place.
The message would be read,
and subscribers would be notified.
And that was no joke.
That really worked, because you would have information
hours or even days before everyone else in Paris.
So, you could make a killing.
So, Reuters today, it's now called Thomson Reuters,
is still in that business.
This was a, the carrier pigeons were a brilliant idea.
They had to keep up with the times,
because shortly thereafter, telegraph was invented,
and the pigeons no longer were the leading technology.
But maybe that was the beginning
of the information age with pigeons.
Now we have beepers, and we have the Internet.
A beeper is something you can carry in your pocket
that beeps when there's financial news.
So, suppose a company makes an announcement that it has,
that it has, say, a new drug that's successful.
In trials, as soon as they make the announcement,
they make a, it then goes out electronically everywhere,
and the beepers start beeping, okay?
And all the investment analysts,
they drop their morning coffee,
they do any, because they
know they've got to act fast.
So, you get this new announcement.
Now, it's t plus 20 seconds.
He's got his drug specialist on the phone.
Okay, what does this mean? Quick.
How much is it going to go up?
And so, the guy says, I don't know.
First thought.
I thought it was going
to go up $2 a share.
Okay, it's only gone up $1 a share.
I'll buy right now.
Now it's two minutes after the announcement.
And then the analyst says, I
thought about it a little bit more.
No, I only think it's $1.50 a share.
Anyway, this is homing in, and
so the price is jiggling around rapidly
as all this is happening for a few minutes,
and then it settles down,
because after, I may be exaggerating,
after 10 minutes, they've kind of gotten it.
They've kind of figured it out,
and it's reached its new level.
Okay?
They'll still be more, they'll be thinking about,
they'll be thinking about the next
morning when they're taking their shower.
And they'll get a better and better,
more refined idea of what the price is.
Okay?
But here's the efficient markets.
You, the next day, read about it
in the Wall Street Journal in the morning.
You're now 24 hours late.
Okay?
So, you call your broker and
say, maybe I should buy this stock.
They've got this new breakthrough.
Your broker might laugh at you, right?
Because you're 24 hours late.
And what do you know, anyway, about pharmaceuticals?
That's where the efficient markets hypothesis is true.
You can't expect to routinely profit
from information that's already out there.
If you're going to profit, you've
got to come up with something faster,
something that you can get faster.
I think this is somewhat what,
David Swenson was referring to yesterday when
he talked about different asset classes that have,
he looked, remember how he talked about comparing
the top quartile and bottom quartile of investment managers
in terms of returns at different asset classes?
Well, the managers weren't able to
beat the bond market very much.
And they weren't, you know, the top quartile
wasn't able to beat the stock market very much.
But when you get to unusual assets,
private equity, which is not traded on stock exchanges,
or absolute return investments that he talked about,
they're unusual, small or rare investments that the
public doesn't have a lot of information about.
And these guys can get ahead on those things.
So, part of what makes Swenson
a success is picking his game.
Even so, the stock market is not completely efficient,
but it's so much more efficient because it's
so many people involved in it and watching it.
So, maybe I should write here, because
this is what we're talking about here,
the efficient markets hypothesis.
I'll write it down.
This is the name for this idea that was coined.
Or sometimes people say efficient markets theory.
They're referring to what Conant and Gibson and other
people had been talking about for a long time.
It was common knowledge.
But the first person to use
this term apparently was Harry Roberts,
a professor at the University of Chicago.
But he was made famous by Eugene Fama.
Who referred to it as Harry Roberts' idea.
Eugene Fama is maybe the best known
finance professor in the country, I think.
He's also at University of Chicago.
And Fama, he's been talked about as
a Nobel Prize candidate for a long time.
He should have won probably, even
though his theory is not entirely right.
I think his chances of getting
it have dimmed a little bit,
because the theory is that he's a genius.
But the theory is not looked upon as
quite such absolute truth as it used to be.
As I said, it's a half-truth.
What I said before, what Conant
said, is all well taken and right.
But there's other nuances and it's not exactly.
When you first read Conant,
you think, the guy is brilliant.
That's what I thought.
This is right on.
Then you read it again and you think,
well, there's a little gambling in the financial markets.
Things don't always work right.
So, he was maybe a little bit too positive.
So, Fama, I can give a little history of this.
It was in 1960.
University of Chicago is kind of the forerunner in this.
In 1960, Ford Foundation gave a grant
to the University of Chicago to assemble
all stock price data back to 1926.
And to get it right.
And so, they set up the Center
for Research in Securities Prices at Chicago.
The Center for Research in Securities
Prices, or CRISP as it's called,
had a Ford Foundation grant
to go to the stock exchanges in the United States
and get all the data and get it right.
Remember, I told you they have splits in stocks?
So, you'll see the price of a share.
And then suddenly the price will fall in half
or maybe it will double
because they changed the units of measurement.
No one had, if you wanted to
know what is the price history of stocks
over the long haul,
no one had ever organized that and
figured out things like that, got it right.
And when were the dividends paid?
When did you actually get the dividends?
So, they said, let's get it right.
Let's put it on, hey, this is really super modern,
a Univac tape.
Okay, that's a computer tape.
Alright?
We'll put it on a tape and we'll
sell it at cost to anybody in the world.
That was, and so the Ford
Foundation, which is a non-profit, said,
good idea, let's do it.
So, that CRISP tape has launched a revolution in finance
because nobody had the data.
They were throwing it away.
It was not used.
How do you know what Sharpe ratios
are if you don't have the data?
I mean, you can find it
in newspapers, but it wasn't organized right.
It wasn't set out right.
So, with the invention of the CRISP tape in 1960,
it really gave impetus to the efficient markets revolution.
And by the end of that decade,
there were thousands of articles testing
market efficiency using the CRISP tape.
And in particular,
in 1969,
Eugene Fama wrote one of the most
cited articles in the history of finance,
was called, Efficient Capital Markets, A Review.
So, he reviews all of
these studies of the CRISP tape.
And it looked authoritative for the first time,
because we were using the whole universe
of stocks all the way back to 1926.
That sounded like a long
time and a lot of data.
And Fama concluded that,
evidence is,
he said it's not uniform.
There are some negative results.
But the evidence is that markets are remarkably efficient.
And this is a truth that we've discovered.
And that, it was really a bombshell,
because he was discrediting, or seeming to discredit,
practically all the investment managers in the country.
It was a huge industry.
And he's claiming,
the successful ones must have just been lucky.
Because the market is so efficient,
that we can't see any way that
you could make money in the market.
And so,
the high point of the efficient markets hypothesis
was probably in the 1970s.
I'll call that the high point.
It seemed at that time,
that all of the scholars were finding
that there was no way to beat the market.
But it started to deteriorate,
the support for efficient markets hypothesis.
And so,
I want to do,
there's been a change in thinking.
Efficient markets is still regarded with respect,
but not the same respect that
it had in 1969 or in 1979.
I have here some,
indication of how thinking has changed
about efficient markets.
I had the textbook that I
used to use for this course.
I've been teaching this course for 25 years.
For Boese,
it wasn't even written when I started.
So, I was using a textbook called Brealey and Myers,
that,
Principles of Corporate Finance.
And I still have all these old editions.
It's a very successful textbook.
But, since I was teaching over all those years,
I went back and looked.
I don't have the first edition of that,
but I have the second edition, 1984.
And I was teaching out of
it in the same class in 1984.
At the end of that book,
there's a chapter on
the seven most important ideas in finance.
And one of the ideas is efficient markets.
And quoting the textbook,
Brealey and Myers say,
security prices accurately reflect available information
and respond rapidly to new information
as soon as it becomes available.
Okay.
They do qualify it in 1984.
Don't misunderstand the efficient markets idea.
It doesn't say there are no taxes or costs.
It doesn't say there aren't some clever people
and some stupid ones.
It merely implies that competition
in actual capital markets
is very tough.
There are no money machines
and security prices reflect
the true underlying value of assets.
Okay. Let me repeat that.
Security prices reflect
the true underlying value of assets.
Okay.
That's almost,
that's a pretty strong statement, right?
But that's efficient market.
They just said it in
their second edition of the book.
Not many people would say that, right?
Trust the stock market.
Don't trust the people you know and love and trust.
Well, they deleted that from later editions of their book.
And I think that's a sign of changes.
So, I was looking at the 2008 edition.
They've now taken on a third author.
They're getting tired of coming out with
more and more editions of their book.
So, they've taken on Franklin Allen from the Wharton School.
They've deleted what I just read.
Now it says,
I'm quoting from them,
much more research is needed
before we have a full understanding
of why asset prices
sometimes get so out of line
with what appears to be their discounted future payoffs.
All right. That's a complete turnaround in the textbook.
So, this is one of the most popular textbooks.
And they've changed completely.
So, I think we have an idea
that started in 19, around the 1960s.
It was somehow
associated with computers and electronic databases
and modern thinking and mathematical finance.
And they kind of went too far with it.
And they concluded that you just can't beat the market.
Another thing I put on the reading list
is a reading from the New Yorker magazine.
It just came out in December.
I thought it was relevant.
It's by Jonah Lehrer.
And the title of the article is
The Truth Wears Off.
Subtitle,
Is There Something Wrong With The Scientific Method?
Well, I don't know if there's anything wrong
with the scientific method,
but I was interested in this article.
Because what the New Yorker article points out
is that a lot of scientists,
and this is outside of finance,
I'm making a parallel here.
A lot of scientists who follow careful scientific procedures
seem to generate results
that are later discredited.
And nobody can figure out why.
It's like the universe is changing.
He gives an example in the New Yorker article.
And this is from drugs.
There's a drug, which are,
a class of drugs called
second generation antipsychotics.
These are used for people who are either
schizophrenic or,
I guess it can be used more generally than that.
Some of the drugs are called
antipsyroquil, zyprexa.
When these drugs were first introduced,
careful studies that passed muster
in the best medical journals
found that they were highly effective.
And they were written up as a godsend.
A way of dealing with problems that
used to weigh on people and,
wonderful, okay.
The medical procedures involve
careful controls on studies, including
a double-blind procedure.
And a double-blind procedure,
when you want to test a drug on human subjects,
you have to have both the subject doesn't know
whether he or she is getting the drug,
and the experimenter who runs the experiment
doesn't know which one is the drug.
So, you give bottle A and bottle B
to the experimenter.
And the experimenter is never told
which one is zyprexa
and which one is a placebo.
And then the experimenter has to write up
a whole report on drug A and drug B.
Not even the drug A.
Not even knowing.
Okay?
This is to eliminate any possible bias.
So, these drugs passed that.
You see what I'm saying?
The controls were right.
Everything was good.
But then, as years go by,
the tests start coming out,
the new attempts to back up,
replicate those, start coming out
more negative.
They didn't disprove the drugs.
They just weren't such wonder drugs
as they thought.
So, how can that be?
And what the article says,
well, it must be that somehow scientific bias,
when there's an enthusiasm for some new theory,
it creeps in,
even if you try to make the strongest controls.
And you say, how could that happen
with a double-blind procedure?
Well, maybe they broke the double-blind somehow.
They tried,
but the guy, experimenter, figured out.
And then he started,
not deliberately fabricating results,
but it's the kind of thing where
one subject says,
I didn't take my Aplafi regularly.
I took two tablets last week.
I have to decide whether to throw this person
out of the sample.
And then I kind of remember that it wasn't,
the drug wasn't working for this person.
And it colors my judgment,
so I throw them out.
And another thing that happens is that
the studies that didn't find it
might have been suppressed.
Someone might have done an Aplafi test
and gotten bad results.
And then showed it to their superior and said,
should I publish this?
And the superior said,
wait a minute,
there must be something wrong here.
Aplafi is wonderful.
So, let's look.
And then they find something that might be wrong.
And he said, you shouldn't publish this,
because they find something.
So, the publication process is biased
for a while.
But eventually it catches up.
So, I think the same thing happened
with the efficient markets hypothesis.
In the initial enthusiasm,
anybody who found that the efficient markets hypothesis
wasn't supported by the evidence,
that person would be told, look again,
maybe you've done something wrong.
And so, that's what happened.
Now, I wanted to do a little bit more history
and describe the concept of random walk,
which is central to the efficient markets hypothesis.
And,
let me start, though,
with a little bit more history.
Technical analysis.
This term goes back,
must be over 100 years.
Technical analysis is the analysis of stock prices,
or maybe other speculative asset prices,
by looking at the market.
By looking at charts of the prices.
And looking for patterns that suggest movements in prices.
The classic text of technical analysis
is Edwards and McGee.
McGee has a famous story about,
he was not a professor,
he was a Wall Street analyst.
And the story about him is that
he believed that you look at the prices
and you can predict prices.
And, in fact, he said,
I don't want to look at anything else.
I just want to see prices.
I'll do plots and I can,
using my judgment,
I can find,
I can figure out what it's going to do.
And so, the story about McGee is,
everyone on Wall Street wants the corner office,
overlooking the World Trade Center or whatever.
He said, I want an interior office with no windows.
I don't want any distractions.
I don't want the real world impinging on my judgment.
So, that's McGee.
But he said that there are certain things
that you see obviously.
For example, resistance level.
When the Dow Jones Industrial Average
approached 1,000,
I think it was in the 60s, 1960s.
It's way above that now, as you know.
But when it first approached 1,000,
technical analysts said,
you know, maybe it's going to have trouble crossing 1,000.
Because that's a psychological barrier.
That sounds magical.
How can the Dow be worth over 1,000?
Wow, I'm going to sell.
And so, the idea was that people would sell
when it approached 1,000.
And it seemed, the technical analysts seemed to be right,
because the Dow bounced around just below 1,000
for a long time.
I guess it was months or a year.
Like it couldn't cross the resistance level.
So, that's one example.
I have another example,
which is from Edwards and McGee's book.
How do I get this?
It's not coming up.
Oh, that's because my thing went into hibernate.
I have to do my password.
There we are.
That's Edwards and McGee.
This is one of the patterns.
McGee was actually a student of psychology.
And he thought,
certain kinds of patterns seem
to have really spooked people.
And this is one pattern,
which he called head and shoulders.
Okay?
That's the head.
That's one shoulder.
That's the other shoulder.
And he said, when you see this pattern,
watch out.
It's going to actually totally collapse,
as it is shown doing.
And so, he had you plotting.
These are stock prices plotted against time.
This is, I don't know what the, these are days.
Each of these points is a day.
And this is from their book.
So, it's a hypothetical.
You hardly ever see such
perfect head and shoulders patterns.
And so, that's one of the patterns.
Maybe that's his most famous.
Edwards and McGee most famous.
Head and shoulders.
So, the question is, does it work?
Does it really work?
Well, in the early 1970s,
when the efficient markets hypothesis was really strong,
Burton Malkiel, who was a professor at Princeton,
and then later he was the
dean of the Yale School of Management,
wrote a book called, A Random Walk Down Wall Street,
which claimed that
technical analysis was bunk.
And he said, many studies
have shown that it doesn't work.
This head and shoulders doesn't work.
None of McGee's, Edwards and McGee's stuff worked.
Well, there were lots of
studies, but I actually met him
at a cocktail party after his book came out.
And I said, you didn't footnote
all those studies about technical analysis.
Where are they?
I can't find them.
I did a search.
Not on the internet.
I did it on something else.
But I was able to search.
And I couldn't find them.
Where are they?
And I found that he didn't have an immediate answer.
I suspected he was extrapolating.
There was a literature on testing market efficiency.
They looked for things
like momentum, whether that continued.
But there was something a
little bit wrong with the literature.
Not many people really confronted technical analysis.
Later, there were people who did look at
some of Edwards and McGee's points, and they
found some element of truth to them.
So, I think the answer is, McGee wasn't a
total idiot, as you might infer from the efficient
markets theory.
But it's not going to make you rich either.
If anything, technical analysis is a
subtle art that can augment trading strategies.
I bet David Swenson doesn't do it.
I don't know for sure.
But let me talk about random walk,
which is a central idea in finance.
And the idea is that, if stock prices
are really efficient, then any change in the market
efficiency is going to be a result of the fact
that the market is going to be a result of
a trade they are going to have.
The reason for that is, if you have
a stock that's very efficient, and it's less than
It's not a trade, and you're spending $1.
It's not a trade.
It's an investment in the market.
Then, any change from day to day
has to be due only to news.
Okay?
And news is essentially unforecastable.
Therefore, stock prices have to
do a random walk through time.
Now, the term – that means that
any future movement in them is always unpredictable.
The changes are totally random.
Okay.
The term, the term, the term,
the term, the term, the term
walk is an important term.
It was coined not by
a finance theorist, but by a
statistician, Carl Pearson, writing in the scientific
journal Nature in 1905.
The movements in some, well, he was thinking theoretically.
Actually, I believe he used the example of a drunk.
Let's take someone who is so
drunk that each step is random.
This person has no direction at all.
It's staggering randomly.
So, he starts out at a lamp pole.
And what would you predict, this is what Pearson asked,
what would you predict is his position in 10 minutes?
He happens to be at a lamp pole.
He's at a lamp pole right now.
And what Pearson said is, well, your best forecast is
that he's right where he is now.
Because you have no bias.
He could go in any direction equally likely.
So, what's most likely?
It's that he stays right where he is.
And what is the probability distribution?
Well, it turns out that the standard deviation around that
point goes up with the square root of n steps.
OK, because each step is independent of the
other, so the square root rule applies.
So, if you're asked to forecast his position after an
hour, that's a lot of steps,
you would say, well, I predict
he's right where he is now,
but I now have a big standard
deviation around it.
Pearson's article had a lot
of, it's a very simple idea.
Among the readers, apparently, was Albert Einstein, and then
Norbert Wiener, the mathematician who had invented
a continuous version of the random walk called the Wiener
process.
So, he's right where he is now.
But it got into finance later.
And in the efficient markets revolution, they started to
realize that stock prices look more
like a random walk than a
head and shoulders.
You look at these head and shoulders patterns, you look
for them, and they're hard to find.
So, what is a random walk?
Let me just define it.
A random walk is where you have a
series x sub t equals x sub t
minus 1 plus epsilon sub
t, where epsilon t is noise.
Just unforecastable noise, mean zero and some standard
deviation.
Ideally, it would be normally distributed.
So, it would have a bell-shaped curve.
And then the math would
be very easy and very simple.
So, you can do that.
But it's not always easy.
So, I want to contrast
that with an alternative, which is
called a first-order autoregressive.
Let me get my notation here.
Let's take a process that starts at 100.
That's like the lamppost.
And we'll say, x sub t
equals, how am I putting this?
I'm going to write it down.
So, x sub t equals, how am I putting this?
Let me write it down.
So, I'm going to write down
100 plus some number of rho,
that's a rho, times x sub
t minus 1 minus 100 plus epsilon
sub t.
So, this is an AR1.
That's first-order autoregressive.
It's like a regression model,
where 100 is the constant term.
And 1 minus rho is the constant term.
And the coefficient of the lagged x is rho.
And we usually require that rho is between
0 and 1, between minus 1 and 1.
Normally, rho is positive.
So, that means that it's mean reverting, but slowly.
You see what this is saying?
First of all, in the special case where
rho equals 1, well, that would be, I wouldn't
call it an AR1 anymore, because
it reduces to a random walk.
If you make rho 1,
then the constant term drops out.
I've got 100 minus 100.
There's no constant term.
And then I've got x sub t equals
x sub t minus 1 plus epsilon t.
That's a random walk.
So, in the extreme case where rho
is 1, I've got a constant term.
In the extreme case where rho gets
to 1, a first-order autoregressive process converges
to a random walk.
I wanted to show you some simulations of
it, if I can make my thing work.
So, let me see.
Here I want to go.
Okay.
Except that I can't see.
This here is a plot I had.
Let's first look at the black line.
The black line is the Standard &
Poor's Composite Stock Price Index in real terms.
I have that from 1871 until recently.
Okay.
That's just there for comparison.
That is the actual stock market.
Okay.
The pink line is a random walk that I
generated using this formula and a random number generator
that generates random normal variables.
Okay.
I started them out at the same level.
But don't they look kind of similar?
I mean, the thing is, if you look at
the stock market without comparing it with a random walk,
it looks like it has patterns in it.
In fact, here's a head and shoulders right here.
Right?
Bang, bang, bang.
When is that?
This is 1937.
This is, when is that?
I'm not sure.
And this is just before the war.
I'm not sure exactly when those.
There's a nice head and shoulders.
Hey, Edwards and McGee are sort of right, right?
It dropped a lot after that.
But, you know, I can find
head and shoulders up here, too.
Right?
And the pink line.
The pink line.
You understand it?
The black line is actual U.S. history.
That's the stock market.
The pink line is a fake
stock line generated with pure random noise.
And the fact that it's going up is just chance.
Now, I can actually use
this program to generate other examples.
So, I'm going to, the black line, this should change.
Let me see.
Make sure it's working here.
Yeah.
The black line is the same.
I'm not going to change the black line.
The black line is history.
I just did a brand new random walk
calculation using my random number generator, which is
there on Excel.
That looks pretty good, doesn't it?
I just did that by, I'm
going to do more for you.
Which one is the real stock market?
I find that hard to tell, right?
This was an insight.
The insight is that people get deceived
when they look at stock price charts.
They think they see patterns.
That pink line is guaranteed to have no patterns,
because I generated it so that there are no
patterns, except random patterns.
But when I look at this pink line,
which just came up, look at that uptrend.
Wow.
That's called a bull market when it goes up.
And I could make all kinds
of theories about why that's happening.
But, you know, those would be fake
theories, because I know what's really happening.
This is pure randomness.
So, I'll do it again.
I can do this forever.
That's another one.
Here, the trend wasn't quite so positive.
Oh, actually, I have to say one thing.
I forgot.
I did put an uptrend in the random walk.
Sorry.
In this simulation, I did add a
constant, so that it pushed it up.
Otherwise, it was a random walk.
I say here, and I forgot what I did.
It was a random walk with trends.
But it doesn't guarantee that it
will go up, because it's random.
I'll do another simulation.
I'll do another one.
See how fast I can do this?
This is the wonder of modern computers.
That one doesn't look – if this were our history, people
would say, the amazing stock market of the first half –
look at that stock market of
the first half of the 20th century.
And we would be devising all
kinds of theories to explain it.
But in fact, it's just nonsense.
It's just randomness.
I'll do a few more.
Look at that.
Boy, that would be a hump
shape for the whole 20th century.
We would have historians trying to figure that one out.
Oh, this one downtrend.
This is a bad outcome.
Jeremy Siegel would not be pleased with this outcome, because
it has the stock market gaining nothing in 100 years.
So, these are all equally likely outcomes.
Look at that one.
If that were the world that we inherited, we would
really think there was a linear trend in the market, right?
People would be making models saying, it just goes
– look at that, how straight that line is.
The point is that you start to see
a sort of reality, which is really just randomness.
That's why Nassim Taleb, a friend
of mine, wrote a book called, Foolish.
He wrote a book called, Foolish.
He wrote a book called, Fooled by Randomness.
That was a great title for a great book.
That people don't understand how
things are just purely random.
And your mind tries to make sense out of them.
And you start looking at patterns,
and the patterns don't mean anything.
So, I can just keep
doing this, but maybe I'll stop.
Look at that one.
Of course, I'm helped along by
the trend that I added in.
So, I want to see
if I can get a downtrend.
Because I put a trend in,
it's hard to get a real downtrend.
That's sort of a downtrend.
That's where there are a lot of negative shocks.
But anyway, what I want to do is – so, you
see the comparison of the random walk with the actual stock market.
So, the actual stock market looks
a lot like a random walk.
You know, one thing is different, though.
Look at this pattern here.
1929, and this is the crash after 29.
You know what?
I'm not getting that in any of my simulations.
And you know why I'm not?
Because I chose a normally distributed shock.
No fat tails.
I didn't put fat tails into my simulation.
And you didn't notice that, right?
But in this simulation, we never see such sudden drops.
So, there's something that you might, if you spend time
searching on it, you might see something not quite right.
But basically, the random walk looks
a lot like the actual stock market.
I'm trying to get one that really matches up.
But I'm not quite succeeding.
That's pretty good, isn't it?
Now, it doesn't show – see, in
this simulation, 1929 wasn't quite as strong.
And the depression wasn't as bad.
Anyway, what I want to do now
is compare the random walk with the AR1.
And so, what I want to
do is go to a comparison.
Now, I'm going to do the same thing,
but I'm going to do it with –
comparing.
Maybe I can go to full screen.
Make it look better.
Where am I? Full screen.
Now – wait a minute.
This is the same thing.
I'm sorry.
What am I – I was trying
to get – maybe it's not working right.
Why do I have the actual stock market?
I can't quite get it.
Oh, I see.
I know what I did.
I'm sorry.
This is – the pink line is
now an AR1 process, which is this process.
So, it's mean reverting now.
And I left the same stuff.
I'm not comparing the random walk with the AR1.
I'm just doing the same thing now.
With the AR1.
Now, the thing about AR1 is you realize
that it wants to come back to 100.
I put a trend in.
So, it's actually coming back to
a linear uptrend in my model here.
What I did is I put
in a time trend as well.
But the point is that
it tends to hug the trend.
It tends to hug the trend somewhat because it
– what an AR1 – I have it here shown
not around a trend, but around 100.
What an AR1 does is, say, rho is a half.
If rho is a half, then it means that if X
of T minus 1 was above 100, last period was above
100, it will be above 100 this
time, but only half as much above 100.
So, it's going back to 100.
Okay.
And then, the next time, it will only be half
again as much above 100 as it was the last time.
So, it goes – it tends
to go back to a trend.
But what I've shown here is a simulation
with a random number generator of an AR1 around
a trend where the trend matches
the actual trend in the stock market.
Now, in this case, there is – this is
not random walk, and there is a profit opportunity.
And the profit opportunity is when it's below trend, buy.
When it's above trend, sell, because it
will tend to come back to trend.
I think it looks a little – I chose
a rho, which was very small, something like a half,
I think.
So, it tends to come rapidly back to trend.
This does look different than
the actual stock market, doesn't it?
It's – you see how much
more it's going to go up?
It's – you see how much it hugs a trend?
So, it doesn't seem to fit as well.
Let me – I can do simulations of this, too.
See, this is different.
This is a different –
you can see the difference, right?
This pink line doesn't look as much like the
actual stock market, because it really wants this trend.
But we saw trendy ones occasionally
by chance with a random walk.
But here, we're seeing it's always on a trend.
And so, in this world, if the stock market
were an AR1, there would be a profitable strategy.
Always buy when it's below trend and sell when
it's above trend, because you know it will come back.
You can see how reliably
this comes back to a trend.
All right.
So, you can see that there's a fundamental difference.
The random walk seems to fit
the data better than the AR1.
The random walk theory says that
stock prices are not mean reverting.
Where they go from today is all random.
If they're above the historical trend, meaningless.
The historical trend is just nonsense.
It's just random.
And forget trends.
Forget anything.
It's always the drunk at the lamppost,
no matter where you are in history.
But this one, if rho is substantially less
than 1, looks a lot different, doesn't it?
With rho equals a half, this
is not the world we live in.
It would be too easy to make money.
All these little oscillations around
the trend, I could profit from.
But in the real world, it's not like that.
Now, but what about, suppose the real
world is AR1 with rho equal 0.99.
What about that?
Well, that's not much different
from a random walk, is it?
It's going to be hard to tell the difference.
So, in the efficient markets theory period, people
were really excited about the random walk hypothesis.
That's why Burton Malkiel's book, A Random Walk Down Wall Street, which
he came out with, I think it was in 1973, right after Fama.
It became a huge bestseller.
It sold over a million copies.
Because at that time, people were
thinking, this is exciting new wisdom.
We've learned the stock market is a random walk.
And there's all kinds of implications for that.
The problem is, and I have to wrap up, the
problem is that the random walk hypothesis wasn't exactly right.
It's sort of right.
You've gotten some insight.
But, you know, maybe the real world
is AR1 with a rho close to 1.
And in that world, there are profit opportunities,
but they take a long time to come.
So, if the real world is AR1 with rho equal 0.99 or 0.98, that means you can buy stocks
when they're below trend, but then you have to wait 10, 20 years for them to get back to trend.
It's like the drunk on the lamp pole.
The drunk is standing next to a lamp pole.
It was a random walk.
But now we put an elastic band around the
drunk's ankle and tie it to the lamp pole.
And it pulls him back.
Now, if we have a very loose elastic, this guy can
wander for a long time, but will eventually be pulled back.
You never know when.
But if you have a tight elastic, then it
would be obvious that the drunk is coming back.
The problem is that the real world seems maybe
to be more like the drunk with the loose elastic.
And so, it's kind of unsatisfying.
You can beat the market.
But, you know, simple trading rules.
Like, Evans, Edwards, and McGee
are not powerful short-run profit opportunities.
In that sense, the efficient markets hypothesis is right.
So, don't forget the efficient markets hypothesis.
I'll repeat what I said at the beginning.
It's a half-truth.
It's half-true.
Remember that.
But don't put too much faith in it either.